{"tossups": [{"question": "Peace in this region was the subject of the Sunningdale Agreement, which failed after bombings perpetrated by the Glenanne Gang. The Shankill Butchers were active in this region. A group from this region carried out a terrorist attack at the Brighton Hotel that failed to kill Margaret Thatcher. Senator George Mitchell developed principles for peace in this region that were adopted in the Good Friday Agreement. For ten points, name this island that was home to Catholic and Protestant violence during the Troubles.", "answer": "<b> Ireland</b> (accept Northern<b> Ireland</b> before \u201cisland\u201d is read; prompt on United Kingdom, but do not prompt on England)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In a court case involving this state, William Wirt was hired by a Native American tribe that was declared a \u201cdomestic dependent nation.\u201d A 1972 case involving this state started a nationwide moratorium on the death penalty; another case four years later, also involving this state, ended it. The<em> Furman</em> and <em>Gregg</em> cases involved this state, which arrested a white missionary for attempting to aid the Cherokee Nation, leading to an 1832 Supreme Court case. For ten points, name this US state involved in the <em>Worcester</em> case.", "answer": "<b> Georgia</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This gospel is the only one where Jesus tries to keep his identity secret, and its manuscripts either have a \u201clonger\u201d ending or a \u201clost\u201d shorter ending. Augustine thought this book was abridged from a longer gospel, but scholars now believe it was a source for the other synoptics. In this book, Jesus says\u201cthe Sabbath was made for man, not man for the sabbath.\u201d For ten points, name this shortest and earliest gospel, the second book of the New Testament.", "answer": "the Gospel/Book of<b> Mark</b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Rogier Verbeek wrote a journal analyzing this event, which was the subject of a BBC documentary subtitled<em> The Last Days</em>. The sun appeared blue and green after the rise of aerosols following this event, which killed over 36,000 people. Though it occurred over 4,000 kilometers away, inhabitants of Rodrigues Island were able to hear this event, which caused the global temperature to fall by over 2 degrees Fahrenheit. For ten points, name this massive 1883 volcanic eruption on an Indonesian island.", "answer": "eruption of<b> Krakatoa</b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Earth Science"}, {"question": "Rebecca Walker\u2019s article denouncing this man introduced \u201cthird-wave feminism.\u201d A<em> New York Times</em> advertisement attacking this man featured 1600 female signatures. This man refused to take a polygraph test, unlike his accuser, who worked with him at the EEOC. This man described his situation as a\u201chigh-tech lynching for uppity Blacks\u201d at his nomination hearing in October 1991. For ten points, name this man who was confirmed to the Supreme Court despite allegations that he sexually harassed Anita Hill.", "answer": "Clarence<b> Thomas</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man declared he would not sacrifice \u201ca frog\u2019s hind legs\u201d for the social experiment that his home country was conducting. The Institute of Experimental Medicine\u2019s Physiology wing was first headed by this man, who studied transmarginal inhibition, an organism\u2019s response to stress. He implanted permanent fistulas in test subjects to measure saliva levels, laying the groundwork for his research in classical conditioning. For ten points, name this Russian psychologist who probably did not ring an actual bell to make his dogs drool.", "answer": "Ivan<b> Pavlov</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name this colonial Massachusetts town where 19 people were executed on suspicion of witchcraft.", "answer": "<b> Salem</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "William Graves led an US expedition that occupied this port city on its way to attempt to rescue the Czech Legion. This port city was known as Haishenwai before its transfer in the Treaty of Aigun. The city of Novosibirsk was founded in 1893 along a railway that ended in this city. For ten points, name this port city whose name means \u201cRuler of the East,\u201d the Eastern terminus of the Trans-Siberian Railway.", "answer": "<b> Vladivostok</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "A Duke of this region fought a civil war with the Armagnac branch of a royal family. The League of the Public Weal was established by a duke of this region; another duke of this region assassinated Louis, the duke of Orleans, in 1410. This region was led by Charles the Bold and Philip the Good, and troops from this region captured Joan of Arc. For ten points, name this region of eastern France, a powerful grand duchy in the late medieval period.", "answer": "<b> Burgundy</b> (accept<b> Bourgogne</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "\u201cHill of Sacrifice\u201d is the translation of the native name of this island\u2019s Punchbowl Crater, which today houses a military cemetery. A mountain on this island was named by British sailors who found calcite crystals nearby. The<em> Resolution</em> visited this island\u2019s Waimea Bay shortly after the death of James Cook on a nearby island. Kamehameha III built a still-extant palace on this island in 1845. Diamond Head overlooks Waikiki Beach in Honolulu on, for ten points, what most populous Hawaiian island?", "answer": "<b> Oahu</b> (do not prompt on Hawaii)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "In a diary written from this location, one man described how his eyes \u201cstarted out from their Orbits like a Rabbit\u2019s.\u201d Albigence Waldo was a surgeon at this location, whose inhabitants had previously been defeated at the Battle of White Marsh. The \u201cBlue Book\u201d was circulated at this location by a man who had previously served the King of Prussia. Over 2,000 men died in this location outside Philadelphia in one season. For ten points, name this location where George Washington\u2019s troops spent a winter during the American Revolution.", "answer": "<b> Valley Forge</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "When advocates for this cause marched on Parliament in 1910, the ensuing police brutality led it to be known as Black Friday. A supporter of this cause took a meat cleaver to Velasquez\u2019s<em> Rokeby Venus</em> a day after another supporter had been arrested. After supporters of this movement were targeted by the Cat and Mouse act, a supporter of this movement was killed after jumping in front of a horse at the 1913 Epsom Derby. Mary Richardson and Emily Davison were Englishwomen who fought for, for ten points, what expansion of political rights?", "answer": "<b> women\u2019s suffrage</b> (accept equivalent answers related to<b> voting</b> rights for<b> women</b> (in the UK); prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Mark Fisher wrote about the idea that this system is inescapable in his book on this sort of \u201cRealism.\u201dAnother thinker wrote that Calvinism was related to the rise of this system in his book on<em> The Protestant</em> <em>Ethic and the Spirit of</em> this concept. Some people argue for a<em> laissez-faire</em> approach to this system, which advances a \u201cfree market\u201d economy. For ten points, name this economic system which allows private ownership of the means of production.", "answer": "<b> capitalism</b> (accept word forms; prompt on \u201cfree market\u201d before mentioned) BONUS:<em> The Protestant Ethic and the Spirit of Capitalism</em> was written by this German social theorist. ANSWER: Maximilian Karl Emil<b> Weber</b> [VAY-bur]", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Sociology"}, {"question": "Indigenous soldiers who fought for colonizing forces in this country were known as lascarins. Portuguese expansion in this country was stopped when one army was annihilated in the Campaign of Danture. The Temple of the Tooth was built in the capital of this island\u2019s Kingdom of Kandy. Under British imperial rule, this island was known as Ceylon. For ten points, name this island where the Portuguese founded a trading station called Colombo, south of India.", "answer": "<b> Sri Lanka</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A rebel against this country\u2019s colonial governments used the nom de guerre Abel Djassi and founded the PAIGC. This country fought anticolonial movements led by Holden Roberto and Samora Machel, and it used the Pink Map to promote its colonial claims. This country\u2019s colonists promoted the ideology of Lusotropicalism, but its colonization of Africa ended in 1975 after the Carnation Revolution. For ten points, name this former colonial controller of Angola and Mozambique.", "answer": "<b> Portugal</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>One artist from this country created collaged images he called prouns. A spiraling monument that was proposed, but never built, in this country was nicknamed \u201cTatlin\u2019s Tower.\u201d This home country of El Lissitzky persecuted the painter of (+)</b><em><b> Black Square</b></em><b> and</b> <em><b>White on White</b></em><b> in the 1920s. The sculpture \u201cworker and (*)</b> peasant unite\u201d was built by an artist from this country, Vera Mukhina. For ten points, name this country in which art was dominated by the \u201cSocialist Realist\u201d style and often depicted its dictator, Joseph Stalin.", "answer": "<b> Soviet Union</b> (or<b> USSR</b> or<b> Union of Soviet Socialist Republics</b>; accept<b> CCCP</b> or <b>Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik</b>; prompt on Russia) (2) <b>This man lost a battle along the Enipeus River after Titus Labienus\u2019s cavalry were</b> <b>shocked by infantry with pikes. After Cicero gave the speech</b><em><b> Pro Lege Manilia</b></em><b>, this man replaced Lucius Lucullus as commander in the (+) Mithridatic Wars. The Lex Gabinia gave this man power to put down Cilician piracy in the Mediterranean. Ptolemy XIII ordered the death of this (*)</b> Roman in Egypt after he lost at the Battle of Pharsalus. For ten points, the First Triumvirate was composed of Marcus Crassus, Julius Caesar, and which man? ANSWER:<b> Pompey</b> the Great", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>This composer wrote a Dervish chorus and a Turkish march for</b><em><b> The Ruins of Athens</b></em><b>, a selection of music to accompany a play written by German diplomat August von Kotzebue. The first opera played in post-war Berlin was a 1945 performance of this composer\u2019s only</b> <b>opera, (+)</b> <em><b>Fidelio</b></em><b>. In 1989 at the Berlin Wall, Leonard Bernstein directed a modified</b> <em><b>Fidelio</b></em><b>. In 1989 at the Berlin Wall, Leonard Bernstein directed a modified</b> <b>version of this composer\u2019s (*)</b> <b>version of this composer\u2019s (*)</b> <em>Choral</em> Symphony. For ten points, name this German composer who used the \u201cOde to Joy\u201d in his ninth and final symphony.", "answer": "Ludwig van<b> Beethoven</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>This man forced the surrender of William Hull by repeatedly marching his troops through the woods to create the impression of bigger numbers. This man allegedly proclaimed \u201cnow</b> <b>here is a man!\u201d after meeting Isaac Brock. This man\u2019s forces swelled after the (+)</b> <b>New</b> <b>Madrid [MA-drid] earthquake was interpreted as an omen. Two years after this man\u2019s brother, (*)</b> known as \u201cthe Prophet,\u201d was defeated at Tippecanoe, this man was killed at the Battle of the Thames. For ten points, name this Shawnee chief who led a namesake confederacy in support of the British during the War of 1812.", "answer": "<b> Tecumseh</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Soon after its establishment, this dynasty was ruled by a set of regents called the Oboi. The Revolt of the Three Feudatories targeted this dynasty, and one ruler of this dynasty was</b> <b>advised by the (+)</b> <b>Jesuit Matteo Ricci. The Aisin Gioro were this dynasty\u2019s ruling clan,</b> <b>and this dynasty, the target of the (*)</b> Taiping Rebellion, produced emperors such as Qianlong and Kangxi. For ten points, name this dynasty established by the Manchu people, the successors of the Ming.", "answer": "<b> Qing</b> Dynasty (accept<b> Manchu</b> before mention)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In 2017, a party leadership election in this country was to include a businessman who refers to himself as \u201cMr. Wonderful\u201d and appears on</b><em><b> Shark Tank</b></em><b>, but Kevin O\u2019Leary dropped out a month before the vote. This country\u2019s leader is under investigation for a</b> <b>potential conflict of interest after he went on a trip to (+)</b> <b>Aga Khan IV\u2019s private island.</b> <b>When asked why this country\u2019s cabinet had gender equality, this country\u2019s leader responded (*)</b> \u201cbecause it\u2019s 2015.\u201d Stephen Harper resigned as leader of the Conservative Party in October 2015 in, for ten points, what country whose Prime Minister is Justin Trudeau?", "answer": "<b> Canada</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>One member of this group attained her nickname for the sound she made when pinched by George Spahn; that member, \u201cSqueaky\u201d Fromme, conducted a failed assassination</b> <b>attempt on Gerald Ford. (+)</b> <b>Roman Polanski was filming in Europe when his wife was</b> <b>killed by members of this group, whose leader believed in the coming of a race war called (*)</b> \u201cHelter Skelter.\u201d This group was formed after its leader moved to San Francisco during the Summer of Love. For ten points, name this criminal \u201cfamily\u201d whose members killed Sharon Tate and several other people.", "answer": "<b> Manson</b> family (accept the<b> Mansons</b>) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker!", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This ruler adopted the national anthem \u201cLet the Thunder of Victory Sound\u201d after</b> <b>successfully capturing the city of Izmail. Assignation Bank, the first to issue paper</b> <b>money in the country, was created under this ruler. In order to protect shipping in the</b> <b>(+) American Revolutionary War, this ruler formed the League of Armed Neutrality.</b> <b>This ruler faced a revolt when (*)</b> Yemelyan Pugachev pretended to be her assassinated husband, Peter III. For ten points, name this enlightened despot, a \u201cgreat\u201d Tsarina of Russia.", "answer": "<b> Catherine</b> the Great (or<b> Catherine</b> II)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}